Ruth Mack Brunswick Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ruth Mack Brunswick Papers 1921-1943 (bulk 1926-1938)
MSS62037
Brunswick, Ruth Mack, 1897-1946
200 items
2 containers
.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Psychoanalyst. Correspondence, patient files, writings, a student training certificate, a concert program, and a newspaper clipping documenting Brunswick’s contributions to psychoanalytic theory including her treatment of Sergius Pankejeff, a former patient of Sigmund Freud referred to as the “Wolf Man” in Freud’s case study, and her work on the pre-Oedipal phase of libido development.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Brunswick, Ruth Mack.; Freud family--Correspondence.; Freud, Anna, 1895-1982--Correspondence.; Freud, Martha, 1861-1951--Correspondence.; Hendrick, Ives, 1898-1972--Correspondence.; Pankejeff, Sergius, 1887-1979--Correspondence.; Pankejeff, Sergius, 1887-1979.; Pankejeff, Sergius, 1887-1979. Sergius Pankejeff papers.
Subjects
Dreams.; Oedipus complex.; Psychoanalysis.
Provenance
The papers of Ruth Mack Brunswick, psychoanalyst, were given to the Library of Congress by the Sigmund Freud Archives between 1960 and 1987.
Related Material
Sigmund Freud’s correspondence with Brunswick spanning the years 1921-1930 is located in the Sigmund Freud Papers in the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Ruth Mack Brunswick are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1897, Feb. 17 Born, Chicago, Ill.
1918 Graduated, Radcliffe College, Cambridge, Mass. Married Hermann Blumgart (divorced 1926)
1922 M.D., Tufts University, Medford, Mass. Began analysis with Sigmund Freud in Vienna, Austria
1925 Established psychoanalytic practice, Vienna, Austria Member, Vienna Psychoanalytic Society, Vienna, Austria
1926 1927 Treated Sergius Pankejeff, a former analysand of Sigmund Freud and the subject of Freud’s “Wolf Man” case study
1928 Married Mark Brunswick (divorced 1937; remarried six months later; divorced 1940) Published “A Supplement to ‘History of an Infantile Neurosis,’” The International Journal of Psycho-Analysis (9:439-476)
1929 1938 Resumed analysis of Sergius Pankejeff on an irregular basis
1932 Became an editor of the Psychoanalytic Quarterly
1938 Left Vienna, Austria, and established a private practice in New York, N.Y. Joined New York Psychoanalytic Society, New York, N.Y.
1940 Published “The Preoedipal Phase of the Libido Development,” Psychoanalytic Quarterly (9:293-319)
1946, Jan. 24 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ruth Mack Brunswick (1897-1946) span the years 1921-1943, with the bulk of material dating from 1926 to 1938. The collection, written in English and German, documents Brunswick’s contributions to psychoanalytic theory expanding the work of her mentor, Sigmund Freud. Featured in the papers are Brunswick’s notes and writings related to her analysis of Sergius Pankejeff, a former analysand of Sigmund Freud and the subject of Freud’s “Wolf Man” case study. In addition to Brunswick’s own notes are notes and writings by Pankejeff including an extensive file of notes recording his dreams. Writings by Brunswick contained in the collection include “A Supplement to ‘History of an Infantile Neurosis,’” which explores her analysis of Pankejeff between 1926 and 1927, and numerous drafts of her 1940 article “The Preoedipal Phase of the Libido Development.” Brunswick first outlined her theories of a developmental phase preceding the Oedipal complex in an untitled work written in 1930. The collection includes a typescript of this early work annotated by Freud.
Correspondence includes letters from members of the Freud family including Sigmund Freud’s wife and daughter, Martha Freud and Anna Freud, letters from psychiatrist Ives Hendrick commenting on Brunswick’s pre-Oedipal article, and two letters from Sergius Pankejeff.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Freud, Alexander, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Anna, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Martha, and Minna Bernays, 1926-1928, 1938, undated (Box 1)
  - Hendrick, Ives, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Fred Bates, 1932, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Mack, Julian W. and Jessie (parents), undated (Box 1)
  - Pankejeff, Sergius, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified (Box 1)
    - Cable to “F. F.” (possibly Felix Frankfurter) from Brunswick regarding conditions in Vienna, Austria, 1933 (Box 1)
    - Carbon copy of letter to “Herr Professor,” undated (Box 1)
    - Fragment of third-party letter containing reference to Brunswick, undated (Box 1)
- Miscellany (Box 1)
  - Brunswick, Mark, concert program featuring work composed by him, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Sigmund, clipping concerning his eightieth birthday, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Society of the Lying-In Hospital, New York, N.Y., student training certificate, 1921 (Box 1)
- Patient files (Box 1)
  - “Caroline J.,” 1927 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1926-1933, 1943, undated (Box 1)
  - Pankejeff, Sergius (Box 1)
    - Notes and writings by Pankejeff (Box 1)
      - Dreams, 1932-1938, undated For additional material see same container, Notes by Brunswick, “Der Wolfsmann”, (3 folders) (Box 1)
      - “Ergänzung zur Kranken,” 1933 (Box 1)
      - “Lida,” undated (Box 1)
      - “Lisa,” undated (Box 1)
      - “Meine Schwester,” undated (Box 1)
      - “Zur Hypochondrie,” undated (Box 1)
    - Notes by Brunswick (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
      - “Der Wolfsmann,” 1923-1936, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - “Wolfsmann Nachtrag,” undated (Box 1)
- Writings (Box 1)
  - Bibliographic notes, undated (Box 1)
  - “Ein Fussfetisch und Seine Beziehung zum Masochismus,” undated (Box 1)
  - “Kastration und Entschädigung in drei Nacheinanderfolgenden Träumen,” undated (Box 1)
  - “The Preoedipal Phase of the Libido Development,” undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - “A Supplement to ‘History of an Infantile Neurosis’” (Box 2)
    - Printed copy, 1928 (Box 2)
    - Typescript, undated (Box 2)
  - Untitled work with handwritten comments by Sigmund Freud, 1930 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified fragments (Box 2)
    - In English, 1932, undated (Box 2)
    - In German, undated (Box 2)